<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nathan 🚂</title>
    <description>CS student and researcher at Illinois.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2018 15:58:39 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2018 15:58:39 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>[notes] Taiwan-China Conflict</title>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;China views Taiwan as a province, Taiwan views itself as an independent nation. Democratically elects its own government&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Despite dispute, the economic relationship b/w China-Taiwan has thrived&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“One China” Principle &lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Trade and commerce between the two began to increase heavily after 1987&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;PRC asserts is bound by the 1992 Consensus between Chinese Communist party (CCP) and Kuomintang (KMT, now Taiwan)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1992 Consensus
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;November 1992 in Hong Kong&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;meeting between Association for Relations Across Taiwan Straits (ARATS) of China led by Wang Daohan and Straits Exchange Foundation (SEF) of Taiwan led by Koo Chen-fu&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;“both sides of the (Taiwan) Straits adhere to the ‘one-China’ principle”&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1979, US reaffirmed&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt; one-China with: “the United States of America acknowledges the Chinese position that there is but one China and Taiwan is part of China.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soon after the US passed the Taiwan Relations Act (TRA), which modified the communique by encouraging defense of Taiwan through supplying of arms. This has ballooned to $25B b/w 2007 and 2018
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;has contributed to US-China friction&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Taiwan president Tsai spoke with Trump recently, first time since 1979&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;History of Taiwan
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ethnic Han settlers arrived in the 17th Century&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ROC governed China for decades, but then fled to Taiwan in 1949 after losin the Civil War to Communists&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Chiang Kai-shek led the ROC in China, until the ROC’s defeat to Communists in Chinese Civil War&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Chiang insisted ROC (and KMT party) on Taiwan represent all of China, which was reaffirmed by US and most Western powers (but later reversed)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In 1979, DC began formal recognition of PRC instead of ROC and ROC lost its seat at the UN to Beijing in 1971&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Taiwan was very repressive with political dissent until 1992 with its first legislative election and 1996 with presidential election&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cfr.org/backgrounder/china-taiwan-relations&quot;&gt;https://www.cfr.org/backgrounder/china-taiwan-relations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[2] &lt;a href=&quot;https://photos.state.gov/libraries/ait-taiwan/171414/ait-pages/prc_e.pdf&quot;&gt;https://photos.state.gov/libraries/ait-taiwan/171414/ait-pages/prc_e.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[3] &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_Civil_War&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_Civil_War&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 19:09:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/notes-on-taiwan-china</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/notes-on-taiwan-china</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Transportation Time-saving Fallacy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We want to believe in a future where the asymptotic behavior of time spent in draining traffic and crowded subways approaches zero. “Imagine reducing [the] 90-plus minute stop-and-go…to a mere six minutes,” says Uber with its dreams of VTOL vehicles&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;. “Choose a route and see how much time [you] can save,” says Hyperloop&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;. Because advancing faster transportation equates to shorter transportation times, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s the transportation time-saving fallacy. Faster transportation does not equate to shorter transportation time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the invention and booming sales of the safety and standard bicycles of the nineteenth century, cities saw urban radius [note: multi-centric city model may be more accurate] expansion as populations moved farther away from city centers. As an interesting side effect, the likelihood of young adults meeting future spouses outside of their municipalities increased&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;. Rates of intra-family marriage decreased, and average distance of origin between spouses expanded from 1 to 10 miles&lt;sup&gt;[4]&lt;/sup&gt;. People were moving much faster on their two-wheeled vehicles (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draisine&quot;&gt;and weren’t pushing off the ground with their feet this time&lt;/a&gt;), and that allowed them to move farther away from urban epicenters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is Marchetti’s Constant (a misnomer because Marchetti credits the initial study to Yacov Zahavi&lt;sup&gt;[5]&lt;/sup&gt;). As our means of transportation improve—whether that be extensive subway networks or manually pedaled two-wheelers—urban sprawl expands with minimal travel time delta. Models of metropolitan Chicago from 2000-2030 show increases of 24% in population and 19% in urbanized land coupled with a mere increase of transportation time from 30 to 31.7 minutes&lt;sup&gt;[6]&lt;/sup&gt;. Very telling is the positive relationship between population density and low-speed public transportation across regions. North American cities’ low-speed transport modes account for 8% of total mobility. European cities’ densities are 4x that and low-speed accounts for 19% of mobility. Asian cities’ densities are 3x that of Europe’s and low-speed accounts for 30% of mobility&lt;sup&gt;[7]&lt;/sup&gt;. Further illustrated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ttsf1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Fig. 1 &lt;sup&gt;[7]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transport’s monetary spend is relatively stable as well: As household food expenditure has decreased over the past decades, spend on transportation costs has remained in its same bracketing. Households with no cars at 3-5% and one or more cars at 10-15%.&lt;sup&gt;[8]&lt;/sup&gt; Zahavi calls these constants Travel Time Budget (TTB) and Travel Money Budget (TMB).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ttsf2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Fig. 2 &lt;sup&gt;[8]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more interesting question to be asked is surrounding why this happens, and my hypothesis is around two main pillars:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Path Dependence and Lock-in
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Switching costs for transportation infrastructure is much higher than that of other technologies. The incremental improvement of traditional railway locomotive to HSR (high speed rail) locomotives requires $1.3M/mi to support the jump from 60 to 110 mph. When topographic conditions require additional clearing, this can hike to $15M/mi&lt;sup&gt;[9]&lt;/sup&gt;, as was the case when the dominant transportation medium shifted from canal to railway. These projects require extreme magnitudes of allocation of capital, so transportation norms stay for extended periods of time, and are “locked in” for periods of ~50 years.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Housing-Transportation Symmetry
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Transportation and Housing spend are largely symmetrical in that the two can’t be separated in an analysis of time and monetary spend: Better transportation enables sprawl b/c people are able to move outwards from the [hypothetical] city center to more affordable housing. This requires the assumption that technology doesn’t change society; rather, people develop technologies to address the changes occurring in society&lt;sup&gt;[10]&lt;/sup&gt;. Taking this as basis, population concentration within cities (from causes out of scope) allows society to develop faster transportation that adheres to the TTB.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So whenever new transportation mediums arise, it’s because of two factors: the necessary technology for a quantum leap (prime mover in the past) and the necessary infrastructure for that technology to bloom into an industry&lt;sup&gt;[11]&lt;/sup&gt;. But I’d also like to add the modification that because people develop technologies to address the changes occurring in society, there’s a third factor of a necessity arising from inventions. In the case of papyrus and paper, it’s a transition away from spoken word like that of Homer’s pieces towards higher levels of science (the invention) that required greater levels of literacy that couldn’t be conveyed and memorized through speech. Similarly, in the case of transportation, it’s the increase in density of cities allowed by inventions like sewage and other feats of civil engineering that require faster transportation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uber.com/elevate.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.uber.com/elevate.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[2] &lt;a href=&quot;https://hyperloop-one.com&quot;&gt;https://hyperloop-one.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[3] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.demographic-research.org/volumes/vol23/33/23-33.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.demographic-research.org/volumes/vol23/33/23-33.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[4] &lt;a href=&quot;http://5by5.tv/criticalpath/199&quot;&gt;http://5by5.tv/criticalpath/199&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
[5] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cesaremarchetti.org/archive/electronic/basic_instincts.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.cesaremarchetti.org/archive/electronic/basic_instincts.pdf&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
[6] &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloudfront.escholarship.org/dist/prd/content/qt047688kf/qt047688kf.pdf&quot;&gt;https://cloudfront.escholarship.org/dist/prd/content/qt047688kf/qt047688kf.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
[7] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0195925596000236&quot;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0195925596000236&lt;/a&gt; (128)&lt;br /&gt;
[8] &lt;a href=&quot;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.454.5721&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&quot;&gt;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.454.5721&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&lt;/a&gt; (14)&lt;br /&gt;
[9] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dot.state.mn.us/passengerrail/mwrri/files/Appendix%20E-Cost%20Estimating%20Methodology.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.dot.state.mn.us/passengerrail/mwrri/files/Appendix%20E-Cost%20Estimating%20Methodology.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (7)&lt;br /&gt;
[10] &lt;em&gt;Paper&lt;/em&gt;, by Mark Kurlansky&lt;br /&gt;
[11] &lt;a href=&quot;http://pure.iiasa.ac.at/id/eprint/3351/1/XB-90-704.pdf&quot;&gt;http://pure.iiasa.ac.at/id/eprint/3351/1/XB-90-704.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (91)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 19:09:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/transportation-time-saving-fallacy</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/transportation-time-saving-fallacy</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>[notes] Bicycle History</title>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EVs can reach something like 150 MPGE. bicycles are about 1000 MPGE, and if you’re really good, all the way up to 9000 MPGE. incredibly efficient
&lt;img src=&quot;https://d2mxuefqeaa7sj.cloudfront.net/s_CB8EDF5018D036A386435E3A4F54F39515825C75E3918B3711E95350428A7ADC_1527921073352_Carl-Benz-at-the-tiller-of-the-improved-1887-Benz-Patent-Motorwagen.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;center&gt;1886 Benz Patent-Motorwagon&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;earliest cars looked like carriages without horses. and a lot also looked like bicycles, like above.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Standard Bicycle
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it was more like a unicycle lol&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;game-changing because first many parts of the 1700s, bicycles had no pedals. It was more like an artificial horse that people would push off with their feet&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1880s was the introduction of the safety bicycle (our modern take on a bike)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;innovated on having two equal wheels, and to have it function, it needed the chain (sprocket) to function
&lt;img src=&quot;https://d2mxuefqeaa7sj.cloudfront.net/s_CB8EDF5018D036A386435E3A4F54F39515825C75E3918B3711E95350428A7ADC_1527921195897_Whippet_Safety_Bicycle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Safety Bicycle, 1880, preceding Patent-Motorwagon&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;these two were massively successful product launches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Safety Bicycle had just gone through a tremendous boom and dozens of international companies were manufacturing bikes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Arms manufacturers in New England began converting their manufacturing systems to create bikes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“Western Method” (Chicago School of Manufacturing) changed from Armory Practice of milling and forging approach (from weapons) to sheet metal stamping for many of the bike’s parts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This allowed for Chicago to really compete against the east coast companies&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;eventually changed women’s freedom. women could start wearing different clothing for pedaling, and Susan B Anthony even said it was a foundational cause for the suffrage movement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;distance between two spouses went from 1 mile to 10 miles when bike boomed
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;even decreased rates of incest, too&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pope Manufacturing Company in Boston began putting two cylinders and some gasoline to create the motorcycle (the chain drive architecture of motorcycles) derived directly from the bicycle
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Adding the first wheels were not far imagination after that…&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the motorcycle really wasn’t designed to replace horses. the correct logic is that adding a motor to a bicycle was completely logical when moving upmarket as the market matures&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in 1903, two bicycle mechanics created the first airplane (famously)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;France between 1900-1910 was the hotbed for automobile innovations (not Germany not USA)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;engine in front, steering wheel, transmission, rear drive, front wheel steering&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Model T was a replication of the technologies of Europe, just improved on manufacturing process&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Austin 7 popularized the pedal setup of modern cars and most UI of driving as it was exported worldwide, originated in Cadillac
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to the contrary, the Model T UI was terribly bad and Austin 7 was monumental in molding that&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manufacturing company and design of cars and airplanes all stemmed from the bicycles
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it was the people relevant in the bicycle industry with their manufacturing capability of bicycles and know-how of designing kinetic vehicles that brought on next generation of technologies (Bicycle Mafia lol)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The people who introduced the car were from the mode of thinking of bicycles (literal definition of disruption). they built the auto and aviation industry without significantly being of it
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;they had no business being in the long-distance transportation industry&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rolls Royce would sell the chassis with motor, then you would commission a coach-builder (formerly coach builders with horses) to put a body on it that suited your taste&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;coach-makers (horses) partners with carmakers
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;the mechanics and engine design (like Rolls Royce) came from a totally different genetic line off there transportation industry&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;they were not the coach-builders, railroad companies, or shipping companies&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Armory Practice - interchangeability of parts developed in 1860-1880 with bicycle industry (called Armory Practice, arms makers in civil war needed to manufacture at large scale and with standardization and really required the reproducibility and interchangeability of parts, transferred to bicycle manufacturers. really a pivoting point in manufacturing b/c of this)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to contrast, the European Method of manufacturing (crafts-based method) was building all up at once - like the marvel and craftsmanship of a whole suit of armor in Europe&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the American Method of manufacturing require little skill at all - canonically, Ford could hire anyone off the street to build his cars
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;didn’t need to be apprenticed, trained up, went to special school for metalworking/woodworking like European Method of manufacturing required&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;trade laws in Europe were largely influential in slowing down Europe’s manufacturing capabilities because of barricades to manufacture individually&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;for one, the US was such a miracle post-war because of the production system, then Japan ran off with it and built an empire (arguably)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Modern Transportation/Ideas Surrounding:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Utility-Theory Travel Demand Model&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;when people start commuting 90 minutes or more, they decide to move into the city, cities start to contract&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;giving people more transport option helps cities spread out. a person who lives 5 minutes from work may decide to move out to 20 minutes away with more transportation&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Faster transportation DOES NOT imply shorter commute times
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Marchetti’s Constant - since Neolithic periods, people have had a constant travel time budget (about one hour)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;So, as transportation gets faster, it’s conceivable to believe that transportation times will not get shorter; rather, people will move farther away, expanding cities.&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2017/02/22/the-american-commute-is-worse-today-than-its-ever-been/?utm_term=.e80d4ea5dae3&quot;&gt;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2017/02/22/the-american-commute-is-worse-today-than-its-ever-been/?utm_term=.e80d4ea5dae3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[2] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0191261581900229&quot;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0191261581900229&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[3] &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marchetti%27s_constant&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marchetti%27s_constant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 19:09:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/notes-on-bicycle-history</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/notes-on-bicycle-history</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>[notes] New Technologies</title>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technology = three factors
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;as a means to fulfill a human purpose&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;as an assemblage of practices and purposes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;as the entire collection of devices and engineering practices available to a culture&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Point three above is the most vital in “innovation”
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New parts are added or subtracted over iterations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dispels the idea of the inventive genius, masterfully crafting technologies out of nothing&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On the flip side, there are phenomena that are independent of humanity and technology
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Once these phenomena are better understood, humanity can harness them to create technologies&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First iterations on new technologies are quite crude but soon converge on something of huge utility. Eventually, however, the marginal gains are outweighed by cost of achieving them, which makes a paradigm shift necessary (aka phenomena)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 mechanisms of innovation:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;novel solutions develop out of small standard engineering advances&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;radical novel technologies develop through the process of innovation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;novel technologies develop by change in their internal parts or by addition to those parts through structural deepening&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the wholesale emergence of new technologies that build and creatively transform industries over time (paradigm shift)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This mechanism of addition, deletion, and paradigm shift makes innovation everlasting&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Infrastructure and technology development have a simultaneous and complementary relationship (prevalent in transportation infrastructure)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;when two are merged together, they enable a technological quantum leap with significant economic effect
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;the combination of iron wagonway&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt; (railroad infrastructure) and steam engine (a prime mover - converts natural energy to mechanical energy)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;when they occur in isolation, the effects are diminished (infrastructure and technology base)
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Monorail railway using sails definitely did not take off&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/new-tech-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;http://ijoc.org/index.php/ijoc/article/viewFile/753/406&quot;&gt;http://ijoc.org/index.php/ijoc/article/viewFile/753/406&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[2] &lt;a href=&quot;http://pure.iiasa.ac.at/id/eprint/3351/1/XB-90-704.pdf&quot;&gt;http://pure.iiasa.ac.at/id/eprint/3351/1/XB-90-704.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (91-92)&lt;br /&gt;
[3] &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wagonway&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wagonway&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 19:09:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/notes-on-new-technologies</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/notes-on-new-technologies</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>[notes] Cable Infrastructure</title>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wired data transfer happens through coaxial cables
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This is the metaphorical highway for internet, telephone, and television cabling&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;These three core services share the bandwidth within coaxial cables&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3 core services = “Triple Play”. Triple Play becoming obsolete. More like 1.5 Play, Internet + Streaming&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Distribution of both “television” and telephone consumption shifting toward streaming and cell, respectively
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Conservative numbers pin tradition television consumption to drop from 86% to 60% in 10 years&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;[2016] “50.8% of households had only mobile service, up from 48.3% a year earlier. Another 39.4% of households had both types of service and 6.5% had landlines only. The survey found 3.2% of homes had no phone connection of any kind.” &lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Renters and young adults are likely to only have a cell phone. Unit economics in favor of phone cord-cutting, cell phones instead. VoIP still more expensive than complete cord-cutting. Large telecom wants to cut cords as well and investing in Internet infrastructure. Revenue for legacy voice systems dropped 11% in 2016. &lt;sup&gt;[2,3,4]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Effects:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1: ISPs can increase bandwidth solely for Internet applications, including streaming
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;If you have half a pie remaining, you can eat it 😛&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Applications like GeForce NOW are compelling side effects&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Foreseeable that ISPs increase Internet prices to offset lost revenue from degradation of Triple Play.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Important question: Does unit demand for Internet bandwidth exceed bandwidth capability of current infrastructure? If not, this option is useless. See point 2.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;2: Does unit demand for Internet bandwidth exceed bandwidth capability of current infrastructure? If not, this could spell interesting opportunity for other uses of network/cable infrastructure already in place.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Underutilized asset. How can it reach maximum efficiency once again? Company that does this right can capture so much value…&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;http://fortune.com/2017/05/04/cut-landline-phone-service/&quot;&gt;http://fortune.com/2017/05/04/cut-landline-phone-service/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[2] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/milestone-for-cellphones-vs-landline-phones/&quot;&gt;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/milestone-for-cellphones-vs-landline-phones/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[3] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.squawkfox.com/landline/&quot;&gt;http://www.squawkfox.com/landline/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[4] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chicagotribune.com/business/ct-att-landline-phone-service-0507-biz-20170503-story.html&quot;&gt;http://www.chicagotribune.com/business/ct-att-landline-phone-service-0507-biz-20170503-story.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 19:09:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/notes-on-cable-infra</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/notes-on-cable-infra</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Level II Chaos in the World</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There are two classes of chaos: level one and two (aka Soros’ Theory of Reflexivity&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; with its objective and subjective realities). The former characterizes systems by a lack of response to prediction and the latter by response to prediction. The oft-cited examples of these are weather (a predictive model can become infinitesimally accurate because the system doesn’t change based off weather reports) and financial markets (predictive models simply cannot be infinitesimally accurate because they affect the system) There are lots of great resources to understand these two classes better&lt;sup&gt;[2][3]&lt;/sup&gt;, and I find the Oscars example&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt; very compelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To better understand level two chaos (subjective reality), I’ve gathered a few examples in this world. This is nothing more than a mental exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Venture Investing in Hot Technologies
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;VCs will rush in troves to hot technologies in expectation of massive returns. This only dilutes the returns with flooded capital, making returns sub-proportional (to expectations) for investors of that specific technology. &lt;em&gt;This does not imply unsuccessful returns&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Traffic Navigation Applications
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Waze + Google Maps use live traffic data to reroute drivers to the most optimal, least trafficked route. As drivers enter said route with least delay, traffic builds up, and this route is again categorized as sub-optimal.&lt;sup&gt;[4]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Antibiotics
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We formulate a new antibiotic, but bacteria mutation survival in response to the antibiotic renders the antibiotic useless over time.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Warnings of Misbehaving Sentient AI
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;People who claim to be oracles of the singularity&lt;sup&gt;[5][6]&lt;/sup&gt; only bring attention to the field, and on the coattails of attention arrives money for R&amp;amp;D spend to accelerate the subjects of their warnings.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Live Music Performance
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Anticipation of a great experience at live music vs. streaming at home draws a large crowd, which detracts from the live experience if standing far away from performer. This is especially true at music festivals.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;https://macro-ops.com/understanding-george-soross-theory-of-reflexivity-in-markets/&quot;&gt;https://macro-ops.com/understanding-george-soross-theory-of-reflexivity-in-markets/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[2] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eqapital.com/Capital_markets/35039_Turning_chaos_into_predictions&quot;&gt;http://www.eqapital.com/Capital_markets/35039_Turning_chaos_into_predictions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[3] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.awardsdaily.com/2015/10/26/the-state-of-the-race-level-two-chaos-system/&quot;&gt;https://www.awardsdaily.com/2015/10/26/the-state-of-the-race-level-two-chaos-system/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[4] This is where I believe there’s an opportunity for traffic coordination applications. Waze + Google Maps have critical mass, and informing drivers of level two chaos and offering traffic coordination on top of routing will lock users into the application.&lt;br /&gt;
[5] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffingtonpost.com/james-barrat/hawking-gates-artificial-intelligence_b_7008706.html&quot;&gt;https://www.huffingtonpost.com/james-barrat/hawking-gates-artificial-intelligence_b_7008706.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[6] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2018/03/13/elon-musk-at-sxsw-a-i-is-more-dangerous-than-nuclear-weapons.html&quot;&gt;https://www.cnbc.com/2018/03/13/elon-musk-at-sxsw-a-i-is-more-dangerous-than-nuclear-weapons.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 19:09:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/level-ii-chaos</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/level-ii-chaos</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>[notes] Silicon Valley History</title>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Early Immigrant influx heavily influenced the networks of today and general ethnic makeup
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Vinod Khosla cites ethnic networks as natural&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Modern examples like Rubrik&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First computers came out of need for larger counting: Adding machine invented by William Burrough (1885) and tabulator for census by Hermann Hollerith (1890)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;~1905: West Coast needed to distribute power and entrepreneurs understood Sierra Nevada dams could provide power
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;EE + high-tension voltage was born out of this need unique to the West Coast&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stanford EE department&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cyril Elwell founded Poulsen Wireless Company (renamed to FTC) out of university by commercializing arc transmitter for radio transmission invented by Danish Valdemar Poulsen. Blew away the competition of East Coast and won Navy contract, the largest customer by far
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;First large-scale commercialization of radio technologies and long distance signal&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;FTC hired Lee DeForest, inventor of audion, to amplify the signals because they would be lost on lost routes. This drastically reduced the cost of radios and made it scalable.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Began a nationwide radio network through this, and it began with first tower in SF in 1910&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Early mainstream application was broadcasting of Presidential election of 1916&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://d2mxuefqeaa7sj.cloudfront.net/s_AEC952BF3F1C7C81E51F0C5A59ED3D2CDC997A4ED4CE31640EC9029A55D8DBEE_1525236302769_78318-004-D80C7B0C.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1916 Election, with Woodrow Wilson emerging victorious&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;center&gt;1916 Election, with Woodrow Wilson emerging victorious&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Long history, even since 1900s, of engineers being business leaders on the West Coast&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bay Area became center of amateur radio technologies because of its maritime proximity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During WWI, radio technology proved to be invaluable for defense, and the government distrusted the west coast from wielding such great power
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Government helped form GE (and its subsidiary RCA) which came to dominate consumer radio applications, and FTC was doomed to serve only the military&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1910s, computing started to come to light in commercial areas like Detroit and NYC, boost coming from bureau
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hollerith’s Tabulating Machine Company (TMC) acquired by new company in NYC, and it changed its name to IBM&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Main tabulating (and computation) customers were insurance and railroad companies&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automating the Office (1920s):
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Typewriters dominated by Remington&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Adders dominated by Burroughs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tabulators dominated by IBM&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cash registers dominated by NCR (National Cash Register lol)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;FTC was the earliest instance of a “mafia” on the west coast (1926-1934)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(Ralph Heintz) Heintz and Kauffman: Installing short-wave radios on ship and airplanes, directly competing with RCA&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(Charlie Litton) Litton Engineering Laboratories: Manufactured tools for vacuum tube manufacturers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(Bill Eitel, Jack McCullough) Eimac: Vacuum tubes for amateur (ham) radio market. Military’s favorite during WWII&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(Gerhard Fisher) Fisher Research Laboratories: Invented metal detector&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Many of these entrepreneurs started out as ham/amateur radio fanatics starting at an early age&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Atomic and nuclear research at Berkeley drew lots of top talent and even the first Nobel Prize to the Bay Area, unified largely by the Lawrence Berkeley Lab (1930s)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Navy was pivotal in developing the area as a consumer of radio technology
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Opened up a base between Palo Alto and San Jose called Moffett Field in 1933&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Followed by Ames Research Center&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1939, HP founded
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Walt Disney was first customer as they purchased HP’s product, the oscillator, for “Fantasia”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://d2mxuefqeaa7sj.cloudfront.net/s_AEC952BF3F1C7C81E51F0C5A59ED3D2CDC997A4ED4CE31640EC9029A55D8DBEE_1525238704427_Integrierter_Quarzoszillator_smial.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Oscillator&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;Oscillator&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stanford professor Willism Hansen and two students formed a company around an amplifier for generating EM waves  at higher frequencies than radio
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Improved radar technologies, vital for WWII pilots&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;As a common theme, Industry+University → Advanced technologies sold to military&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Elsewhere:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Alan Turing presents abstract idea of a Turing machine (1937)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;John Von Neumann created simple architectural idea for computer storing both instructions and memory, spread from Princeton due to its open research policy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bell Labs formed in NYC (1925)
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Proposal by George Stibitz to create binary relay-based arithmetic machine, an it was commercialized and named as “Model K”&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://d2mxuefqeaa7sj.cloudfront.net/s_AEC952BF3F1C7C81E51F0C5A59ED3D2CDC997A4ED4CE31640EC9029A55D8DBEE_1525239232302_MonroeKA-574-IMG_0672-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Model K&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Model K&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Konrad Zuse in Germany created first hardware implementation of universal Turing machine called the “Z3” (1941)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HP Case Study
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Began as contractors building miscellaneous electrical projects like lane signaling for bowling alley&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1943: Produced electrical lab testing equipment, $1M revenue, most from Navy (WWII)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Management by Walking Around (MBWA): Instead of waiting for subordinates to report, management would walk around and actively engage people
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Open door policy - sort of like open office today&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Harmony between founders: Ask a founder one question, you’ll get same answer from other founder -John Granger&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Packard presented rules to deal with people in 1958 Sonoma Retreat (repeated in On Leadership)
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Think about the other person first&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Built up the other person’s sense of importance and don’t forget to respect the other person’s “personality rights” (the right to be different)…empathize&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Give sincere appreciation. Don’t openly try to reform people&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Eliminate the negative. Focus on solutions and not on what can’t be done&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Examine your first impressions on people, products, and companies&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Take care of details (tone of voice, smiling, greeting, appearance)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Develop genuine interest in people&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Firing was always the last resort&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many technologies used by US during the war (and later commercialized) were imported, like a follower nation in 1940
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tape recorder, commercialized as a subsequent product to Ampex’s airborne radar antennas, was manufactured after a soldier took it from Germany. It was invented by Fritz Pfleumer.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;First computer created in Britain called the Colossus Mark  1 created in 1943. Harvard Mark 1 followed in 1944. This was the first computer programmed by punched paper tape.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;couldn’t store programs, so women had to feed punched programs into the machine sequentially.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After WWII industrial production rose by over 50% in a span of 10 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 19:09:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/notes-on-sv-history</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/notes-on-sv-history</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>[notes] Writing Well</title>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid the Obvious Content
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When beginning to write, think of all the first arguments that come to mind and compile them into a list. Then when you’re actually writing, avoid all of these topics.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Forces you to think of and write down contrarian ideas&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take the Less Usual Side
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Take the side (there may be 3+ sides) that seems hardest, least defensible&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“Don’t worry too much about figuring out what the instructor thinks about the subject so that you can cuddle up with him”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;e.g. when tasked with writing about dogs, argue that they possess “a vacuity of mind and an inconstancy of purpose; that the dogs you have known most intimately have been mangy, ill-tempered brutes, incapable of instruction”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slip Out of Abstraction
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Speaking in generalities dulls the reader’s mind&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;AVOID “football is bad for the colleges,” “it has become too commercial,” “football is big business,” “it is bad for the players,” etc.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Like great writers, write from the generality, the abstract statement, to the concrete example, the facts and figures, the illustrations.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;e.g. REPLACE “Sororities teach girls the social graces.” WITH “Sorority life teaches a girl how to carry on a conversation while pouring tea, without sloshing the tea into the saucer.”&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get Rid of Obvious Padding
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Chopping down sentences is derived by replacing empty sentences with that of the above&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Call a Fool a Fool
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;e.g. “In my opinion, the principal of my high school acted in ways that I believe every unbiased person would have to call foolish.” → “My high school principal was a fool.”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Avoid “in my opinion,” “it seems to me,” “as I see it,” etc.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beware of Pat Expressions
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Avoid “to all practical intents and purposes,” “the pure and simple truth,” “from where I sit,” “the time of his life,” “to the ends of the earth,” etc.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;These are simply fillers&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Colorful Words
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Simple: More descriptive words that bring more color are favorable most of the time&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Don’t drown the reader in it though&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Colored Words
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;aka connotations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Every utterance of a word carries all previous utterances with it&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Colorless Words
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Beware of words like circumstances, cases, instances, aspects, factors, relationships, attitudes, eventualities. They are many times just padding with little value.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 19:09:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/post/notes-on-writing-well</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/post/notes-on-writing-well</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
